Chapter 36. The quarter deck.
Enter Ahab. Then all.
It was not a great while after the affair of the pipe that one morning,
shortly after breakfast, Ahab, as was his want, ascended the cabin gang way to
the deck. There most sea captains usually walk at that hour as country
gentlemen after the same meal take a few turns in the garden. Soon his steady
ivory stride was heard as to and fro he paced his old rounds upon planks so
familiar to his tread that they were all over dented like geological stones with
the peculiar mark of his walk. Did you fixly gaze too upon that ribbed indented
brow, there also you would see still stranger footprints, the footprints of
his one unsleeping, everpacing thought.
But on the occasion in question, those dents looked deeper, even as his nervous
step that morning left a deeper mark.
And so full of his thought was Ahab that at every uniform turn that he made now
at the main mast and now at the binnacle, you could almost see that
thought turn in him as he turned and pacing him as he paced, so completely
possessing him indeed that it all but seems the inward mold of every outer movement.
Do you mark him? Flask whispered Stub.
The chick that's in him pecks the shell.
It will soon be out.
The hours wore on. Ahab now shut up within his cabin. Anon pacing the deck
with the same intense bigotry of purpose in his aspect. It drew near the close of
day. Suddenly he came to a halt by the bull works, and inserting his bone leg
into the augur hole there, and with one hand grasping a shroud, he ordered
Starbucks to send everybody a.
Sir, said the mate, astonished at an order seldom or never given on shipboard
except in some extraordinary case. Send everybody aft, repeated Ahab. Mastads there. Come down.
When the entire ship's company were assembled, and with curious and not
wholly unapprehensive faces were eyeing him, for he looked not unlike the
weather horizon when a storm is coming up. Ahab, after rapidly glancing over
the bull works, and then darting his eyes among the crew, started from his
standpoint, and as though not a soul were nigh him, resumed his heavy turns
upon the deck, with bent head and half slouched hat, he continued to pace,
unmindful of the wandering whispering among the men, till stub cautiously
whispered to Flast that Ahab must have summoned them there for the purpose of
witnessing a pedestrian feat. But this did not last long. Vehemently pausing,
he cried, "What do you do when you see a whale, men?" "Sing out for him!" was the
impulsive rejoinder from a score of clubbed voices. "Good!" cried Ahab, with
a wild approval in his tones, observing the hearty animation into which his
unexpected question had so magnetically thrown them. "And what do you do next,
man? lower away and after him. And what tune is it you pull to men? A dead whale
or a stove boat?
More and more strangely and fiercely glad and approving grew the countenance
of the old man at every shout, while the mariners began to gaze curiously at each
other, as if marveling how it was that they themselves became so excited at
such seemingly purposeless questions.
But they were all eagerness again, as Ahab, now half revolving in his pivot
hole, with one hand reaching high up a shroud, and tightly, almost convulsively
grasping it, address them thus.
All ye mastaders have before now heard me give orders about a white whale. Look
ye, do you see this Spanish ounce of gold? Holding up a broad, bright coin to
the sun. It is a $16 piece, men. Do you see it, Mr. Starbucks? Hand me yon top
mall. While the mate was getting the hammer, Ahab, without speaking, was
slowly rubbing the gold piece against the skirts of his jacket as if to
heighten its luster, and without using any words, was meanwhile lowly humming
to himself, producing a sound so strangely muffled and inarticulate that
it seemed the mechanical humming of the wheels of his vitality in him. Receiving
the top mall from Starbucks, he advanced towards the main mast with the hammer
uplifted in one hand, exhibiting the gold with the other, and with a high
raised voice, exclaiming, "Whosoever of ye raises me a white-headed whale with a
wrinkled brow and a crooked jaw.
Whosoever of ye raises me that white-headed whale with three holes
punctured in his starboard fluke. Look ye, whosoever of you raises me that same
white whale, he shall have this gold ounce, my boys. Huzzah! Huzzah!" cried
the seaman, as with swinging tarpins, they hailed the act of nailing the gold
to the mast. "It's a white whale, I say," resumed Ahab as he threw down the
top mall. "A white whale! Skin your eyes for him, men. Look sharp or white water.
If you see but a bubble, sing out.
All this while, Tashego, Dagu, and Quiquake had looked on with even more
intense interest and surprise than the rest, and at the mention of the wrinkled
brow and crooked jaw, they had started as if each was separately touched by
some specific recollection.
Captain Ahab, said, Tashego, that white whale must be the same that some call
Moby Dick. Moby Dick shouted Ahab. Do you know the white whale then Tash?
Does he fanail a little curious sir before he goes down? said the gayheader deliberately.
And he has a curious spout too, said Dagu. Very bushy even for a pariceti.
And mighty quick, Captain Ahab. And he have one, two, three. Oh, good many iron
in him. Hide too, Captain cried Quiquake disjointedly. All twisy tea uh be twis
like him. Him him faltering hard for a word and screwing his hand round and
round as though unccoring a bottle. Like him him. Corkcrew cried Ahab. I qui qu
the harpoons lie all twisted and wrenched in him. I dagu his spout is a
big one like a whole shock of wheat and white as a pile of our Nantucket wool
after the great annual sheep shearing. I Tashego and he fantales like a split jib
in a squall. Death and devils men. It is Moby Dick you have seen. Moby Dick. Moby Dick.
Captain Ahab, said Starba, who with stub and flask had thus far been eyeing his
superior with increasing surprise, but at last seemed struck with a thought,
which somewhat explained all the wonder.
Captain Ahab, I have heard of Moby Dick, but it was not Moby Dick that took off
thy leg. Who told thee that? Cried Ahab, then pausing.
I Starbucks I my hearties all around. It was Moby Dick that dismastered me. Moby
Dick that brought me to this dead stump I stand on now. I I he shouted with a
terrific loud animal so like that of a heartstricken moose. I I it was that
oursided white whale that razied me, made a poor pegging lober of me forever
and a day. Then tossing both arms with measurless imprecations, he shouted out, "I I
chase him round good hope and round the horn and round the Norway mastrom and
round pditions flames before I give him up. And this is what you have shipped
for men to chase that white whale on both sides of land and over all sides of
the earth till he spouts black blood and rolls fin out. What say you men? Will
you splice hands on it now? I think you do look brave.
I I shouted the harpooners and the seaman running closer to the excited old
man. A sharp eye for the white whale. A sharp lance for Moby Dick.
God bless ye. He seemed to half sobb and half shout. God bless ye men. Steward,
go draw the great measure of grog.
But what's this long face about, Mr.
Starbucks? Wilt thou not chase the white whale? Art not game for Moby Dick?
I am game for his crooked jaw and for the jaws of death too, Captain Ahab, if
it fairly come in the way of the business we follow. But I came here to
hunt whales, not my commander's vengeance. How many barrels will thy
vengeance yield thee? Even if thou getest it, Captain Ahab, it will not
fetch thee much in our Nantucket market.
Nantucket market.
But come closer, Starbucks. Thou require us a little lower layer. If money is to
be the measurer, man, and the accountants have computed their great
counting house the globe, by girdling it with guineies one to every three parts
of an inch. Then let me tell thee that my vengeance will fetch a great premium here.
He smites his chest, whispered Stub.
What's that for? me thinks it rings most vast but hollow vengeance on a dumb brute cried
Starbucks that simply smokeote thee from blindest instinct madness to be enraged
with a dumb thing Captain Ahab seems blasphemous arry yet again the little lower layer
all visible objects man are but as paceboard masks but in each event in the
living act, the undoubted deed. There some unknown but still reasoning thing
puts forth the moldings of its features from behind the unreasoning mask. If man
will strike, strike through the mask.
How can the prisoner reach outside except by thrusting through the wall?
To me, the white whale is that wall shoved near to me.
Sometimes I think there's not beyond.
But is enough. He tasks me. He heaps me.
I see in him outrageous strength, but with an inscrable malice sinuing it.
That inscrable thing is chiefly what I hate. And be the white whale agent or be
the white whale principal. I will wreak that hate upon him. Talk not to me of
blasphemy, man. I'd strike the sun if it insulted me. Or could the sun do that?
Then I could do the other, since there is ever a sort of fair play herein,
jealousy presiding over all creations.
But not my master man is even that fair play. Who's over me? Truth hath no confines.
Take off thine eye more intolerable than fiend's glarings as adultish stare.
So, so thou reddenest and palest. My heat has melted thee to anger glow. But
look ye star, what is said in heat. That thing uns says itself. There are men
from whom warm words are small indignity. I meant not to incense thee.
Let it go.
Look, see yonder Turkish cheeks of spotted taawn. living, breathing
pictures painted by the sun. The pagan leopards, the unwrecking and unworipping
things that live and seek and give no reason for the torid life they feel. The
crew man, the crew, are they not one and all with Ahab in this matter of the
whale? See Stub, he laughs. See yonder Chillion, he snorts to think of it.
Stand up amidst the general hurricane.
Thy one tossed sapling cannot Starbucks.
And what is it? Reckon it. It is but to help strike a fin. No wondrous feat for
Starbucks. What is it more? From this one poor hunt then the best lance out of
all Nantucket. Surely he will not hang back when every form hand has clutched a
wet stone. Ah constraining sees thee. I see the billow lifts thee. Speak. But speak
I I thy silence then that voices thee.
Aside something shot from my dilated nostrils.
He has inhaled it in his lungs.
Starbucks now is mine. Cannot oppose me now without rebellion.
God keep me. Keep us all. murmured Starbucks lowly.
But in his joy at the enchanted, tacit acquiescence of the mate, Ahab did not
hear his foreoding invocation, nor yet the low laugh from the hold, nor yet the
preaging vibrations of the winds in the cordage, nor yet the hollow flap of the
sails against the mass, as for a moment their hearts sank in. For again
Starbucks downcast eyes lighted up with the stubbornness of life. The
subterranean laugh died away. The winds blew on. The sails filled out. The ship
heaved and rolled as before.
Ah ye admonitions and warnings. Why stay ye not when you come? But rather are you
predictions than warnings, you shadows, yet not so much predictions from without
as verifications of the foregoing things within. For with little external to
constrain us, the innermost necessities of our being, these still drive us on.
The measure, the measure, cried Ahab, receiving the brimming pewtor and
turning to the harpooners, he ordered them to produce their weapons. then
ranging them before him near the capston with their harpoons in their hands,
while his three mates stood at his side with their lances and the rest of the
ship's company formed a circle around the group. He stood for an instant
searchingly eyeing every man of his crew. But those wild eyes met his as the
bloodshot eyes of the prairie wolves meet the eye of their leader. air. He
rushes on at their head in the trail of the bison, but alas, only to fall into
the hidden snare of the Indian.
Drink and pass, he cried, handing the heavy charged flag to this nearest
seaman. The crew alone now drink round with it. Round short drafts, long
swallows, men. It is hot as Satan's hoof. So, so it goes round excellently.
It spiralizes in ye, forks out at the serpent's snapping eye. Well done.
Almost drained. That way it went. This way it comes. Hand at me. Here's a
hollow. Men, you seem the years so brimming. Life is gulped and gone.
Steward refill.
Attend now, my braves. I have mustered you round this capston, and you mates
flank me with your lances, and you harpooners stand there with your irons,
and you stout mariners, ring me in that I may in some sort revive a noble custom
of my fisherman fathers before me. Oh men, you will yet see that, huh, boy,
come back. Bad pennies come not sooner, handed me. Why now this putwer had run
brimming again? Wart not thou St.
Vitis's imp. Away thou au advance ye mates cross your lances full
before me. Well done. Let me touch the axis. So saying with extended arm he
grasped the three level radiating lances at their cross centers while so doing
suddenly and nervously twitched them.
Meanwhile, glancing intently from Starbucks to stub, from stub to flask,
it seemed as though by some nameless interior volition, he would fain have
shocked into them the same fiery emotion accumulated within the laden jar of his
own magnetic light. The three mates quailed before his strong, sustained,
and mystic aspect. Stub and flask looked sideways from him. The honest eye of
Starbucks fell downright.
In vain, cried Ahab. But maybe it is well, for did ye three but once take the
full forced shock, then my own electric thing that perhaps had expired from out
me. Per chance too, it would have dropped you dead. Per chance you need it
not. Down, lances. And now, ye mates, I do appoint ye three cupbearers to my
three pagan kinsmen there. Yan three most honorable gentlemen and noblemen,
my valiant harpooners.
Disdain the task? What? When the great pope washes the feet of beggars, using
his tiara for you? Oh, my sweet cardinals, your own condescension, that
shall bend you to it. I do not order ye, ye will it. Cut your seasings and draw
the poles, you harpineers.
Silently obeying the order, the three harpooners now stood, with the detached
iron part of their harpoons some 3 ft long, held barbs up before him. Stab me
not with that keen steel. Can't them.
Can't them over. Know you not the goblet end. Turn up the socket. So, so now you
cupbearers advance the irons. Take them.
Hold them while I fill.
Forthw with slowly going from one officer to the other, he brimmed the
harpoon sockets with the fiery waters from the pewtor.
Now three to three ye stand. Commend the murderous chalicees. Bestow them, ye who
are now made parties to this indissoluble league. Ha, Starbucks. But
the deed is done. Yonratifying son now waits to sit upon it. Drink ye
harpineers. Drink and swear ye men that man the deathful whaleboats bow. Death
to Moby Dick. God hunt us all if we do not hunt Moby Dick to his death. The
long barbed steel goblets were lifted and to cries and maladictions against
the white whale. The spirits were simultaneously quathed down with a hiss.
Starbucks pald and turned and shivered once more and finally the replenished
pewtor went the rounds among the frantic crew. When waving his free hand to them,
they all dispersed and Ahab retired within his cabin.